Finding aid for the Sylvia Plath collection MRBC.MS.00045
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
- Writings, 1949-1963; 1; 9.3 linear feet (17 boxes; 8 oversize folders)
  - Poetry, approximately 1950-2008; 5; 7.2 linear feet (12 boxes; 8 oversize folders)
    - Printed version of "Wreath for a Bridal," "Dream with Clam-Diggers," "Strumpet Song," Metamorphosis," "Two Sisters of Persephone," "Epitaph for Fire and Flower.", 1957 January (Box 14.1, Folder 299, Item 3)
      Printed version from Poetry volume 88, pages 231-37.
    - Printed version of "Wreath for a Bridal", 1957 January (Box 14.1, Folder 299, Item 4)
      Printed version from Poetry volume 88, pages 231-37. Annotations by Aurelia Plath.
    - Printed version of "Wreath for a Bridal", 1970 (Box 14.1, Folder 299, Item 5)
      Printed version: Frensham, Farnham, Surrey, England: The Sceptre Press, 1970. Copy number 68 of an edition of 100 copies.
    - Typescript of "Wuthering Heights", between 1961 August and 1962 December (Box 14.1, Folder 300, Item 1)
    - Typescript of "Wuthering Heights", 1961 September (Box 14.1, Folder 300, Item 2)
      Typescript of "Wuthering Heights" annotated by Sylvia Plath. Date and "New Statesman" annotated at the top in Sylvia Plath's hand.
    - Printed version of "Wuthering Heights", 1962 March 16 (Box 14.1, Folder 300, Item 3)
      Printed version from New Statesman volume 63, page 390.
    - Typescript of "Yado: The Grand Manor", not after 1959 October (Box 14.1, Folder 301, Item 1)
      Typescript carbon of "Yaddo: The Grand Manor" annotated by Sylvia Plath. "C S Monitor: OCt 13 $10" annotated at the top in Sylvia Plath's hand.
    - Printed version of "Yado: The Grand Manor", 1959 October (Box 14.1, Folder 301, Item 2)
      Printed version from The Christian Science Monitor with photocopy of complete page in CSM.
      With tape residue; removed from SP's scrapbook.
    - Typescript of "Yadwigha, on a Red Couch, Among Lilies", between 1958 March and September (Box 14.1, Folder 302, Item 1)
      Typescript of "Yadwigha, on a Red Couch, Among Lilies". Title is underlined in red pencil and "C S Monitor" is annotated at the top in Sylvia Plath's hand.
    - Printed version of "Yadwigha, on a Red Couch, Among Lilies", 1959 March 26 (Box 14.1, Folder 302, Item 2)
      Two copies of the printed version from The Christian Science Monitor 1959 Mar 26, page 8, annotated by Sylvia Plath. One copy annotated by Plath and with tape residue.
      Removed from SP's scrapbook.
    - Holograph of "Years", 1962 November 16; 3 pages; Written on pink Smith College memorandum paper. (Box 14.1, Folder 303, Item 1)
    - Revised typescript of "Years", undated; 1 pages; Typed on pink Smith College memorandum paper. (Box 14.1, Folder 303, Item 2)
    - Revised typescript of "Years", 1962 November 16; 1 pages; Typed on pink Smith College memorandum paper. (Box 14.1, Folder 303, Item 3)
    - Photocopy of a typescript of "Years", 1962 November 16; 2 pages (Box 14.1, Folder 303, Item 4)
      Original filed with "The Fearful"
      Photocopy of original and carbon typescripts of "Years" revised. The back of page 1 has Sylvia Plath's "The Fearful": item 2, page 1.
    - Typescript of "Years", 1962 November 16; 1 pages (Box 14.1, Folder 303, Item 5)
      Carbon typescript of "Years", revised.
    - Typescript of "Years", 1962 November 16; 3 pages (Box 14.1, Folder 303, Item 6)
      Original and carbon typescripts of "Years."
    - Printed version of "Years," "The Bee Meeting," "Stings," "Cut," "Letter in November," "The Couriers," and Mary's Song", 1963 April (Box 14.1, Folder 303, Item 7)
      Printed version from The London Magazine new series, volume 3, number 1, page 32. Page 25 is headed "Seven Poems." Annotated by Aurelia Plath.
    - Typescript of "You're", not after 1961 June (Box 14.1, Folder 304, Item 1)
      Typescript of "You're" corrected and annotated by Sylvia Plath. "Harper's London Magazine BBC" is annotated at the top in Sylvia Plath's hand.
    - Typescript of "You're", between 1961 August and 1962 December (Box 14.1, Folder 304, Item 2)
      Typescript of "You're" with "(Harper's)/(London Magazine)/(BBC)" typed at the top.
    - Printed version of "You're", 1961 June (Box 14.1, Folder 304, Item 3)
      Two copies of printed version from Harper's magazine, volume 222, page 40. Annotated by Sylvia Plath.
    - Printed version of "You're", 1961 June (Box 14.1, Folder 304, Item 4)
      Two copies of printed version from Harper's magazine, volume 222, page 40. Annotated by Aurelia Plath.
    - Typeset proof of "You're," "Zoo Keeper's Wife," "Small Hours," "Parliament Hill Fields," "Whitsun," "Leaving Early," "In Plaster.", probably 1961 (Box 14.1, Folder 304, Item 5)
      Typeset proof for publication in The London Magazine with heading "Seven Poems", corrected and revised and initialed by Sylvia Plath.
    - Printed version of "You're," "Zoo Keeper's Wife," "Small Hours," "Parliament Hill Fields," "Whitsun," "Leaving Early", 1961 August (Box 14.1, Folder 304, Item 6)
      Printed version from The London Magazine new series 1, pages 5-10.
    - Typescript of "You're", undated (Box 14.1, Folder 304, Item 7)
      Carbon typescript of "You're" numbered 38, probably for Ted Hughes' book Ariel.
    - Photocopy of printed version of "You're," "Zoo Keeper's Wife," "Small Hours," "Parliament Hill Fields," "Whitsun," and "Leaving Early", 1961 August (Box 14.1, Folder 304, Item 8)
      Photocopy of printed version from The London Magazine, new series, volume 1, number 5, page 6. Page 5 is headed "Six Poems." Annotations by Aurelia Plath.
    - Printed version of "You're", 1966 (Box 14.1, Folder 304, Item 9)
      Gift of Ann Safford Mandel, Smith College class of 1953, 10/22/1977.
      Printed version in Critical Quarterly Poetry Supplement Number 7, New Poems 1966 number 7, page 13.
    - Typescript of "Zoo Keeper's Wife", undated (Box 14.1, Folder 305, Item 1)
      Typescript of "Zoo Keeper's Wife" annotated and corrected by Sylvia Plath, including autograph correction of a typing error. "London Magazine" is annotated at the top in Sylvia Plath's hand.
    - Printed version of "Zoo Keeper's Wife," "You're," "Small Hours," "Parliament Hill Fields," "Whitsun," and "Leaving Early.", 1961 August (Box 14.1, Folder 305, Item 2)
      Pinted version from The London Magazine, new series, volume 1, number 5, pages 5-6. Page 5 is headed "Six Poems." Annotations by Aurelia Plath.
    - Poem subjects, 1959-1962
      Most of these manuscript lists of potential poem subjects, as well as possible poem titles, were written by Ted Hughes, with some additions by Sylvia Plath, and annotations by both Ted Hughes and Sylvia Plath. The lists are written on various sizes of different kinds of paper. Items were dated when cataloged based on internal evidence (e.g., some dates do appear on some pages) and external sources (e.g., dates on which certain poems are known to have been composed and/or published). Notes on how suggested dates were arrived at are written on the item folders. The first entry on each list is used as an item title.
      The items are listed here roughly in chronological order.
      - List of poem subjects beginning "Stains", probably 1959; 2 pages 2 pages (1 leaf) (Box 14.2, Folder 306, Item 1)
        List of poem subjects with a holograph poem of Ted Hughes beginning, "I'm a canteen worker" on the back of the page.
      - List of poem subjects beginning "Old woman at dawn", probably 1959; 1 pages (Box 14.2, Folder 306, Item 2)
      - List of poem subjects beginning "An English farmer", after 1960; 1 pages (Box 14.2, Folder 306, Item 3)
        "Private Ground" is writen in Plath's hand. The back of the page has a Sussex, UK house description on the letterhead of Wm. Wood, Son & Gardner (half sheet only).
      - List of poem subjects beginning "Queen Mary's...", between summer 1959 and 1961; 1 pages; List on pink Smith College memorandum paper. (Box 14.2, Folder 306, Item 4)
      - List of poem subjects beginning "Water drop in underground grotto", after 1960 April 1 - 1962 (Box 14.2, Folder 306, Item 5)
        "The Pheasant", "Rabbit Snares", "Sheep by moonlight & Christ tree", and "Owl mobbed by birds" are in Plath's hand. The back of the page is a carbon typescript of a page numbered 53 of Ted Hughes' play The Calm.
      - List of poem subjects beginning "Gulls, coming into Southampton", 1960 July 5-1962 (Box 14.2, Folder 306, Item 6)
        Plath has written some poem titles next to Hughes subjects, including "On Deck," "The Hanging Man," "Crossing the Water," "Sleep in the Mohave Desert." Also in Plath's hand: "Candles, Night Feeding, The Dwarf" and two lines beginning "The moon's round O-mouth of sorrow".
      - List of poem subjects beginning "The weight of things", probably 1961 February; 1 pages; List on the interior of an envelope. (Box 14.2, Folder 306, Item 7)
      - List of poem subjects beginning "Finisterre", maybe 1961; List on cardboard. (Box 14.2, Folder 306, Item 8)
    - Submission lists, 1959 September-1963 February 4; 4 items (Box 14.2, Folder 307)
      These typed and handwritten lists by Sylvia Plath record details of where she submitted her poems for publication, including dates of a poem's acceptance and/or amount paid to her. There is extensive handwritten annotation, underlining, and markings in red pencil and ink.
    - Lists of publications, 1959-1961
      This folder includes various typed lists by Sylvia Plath of her published writing (poems, articles, and stories), usually including the title, where published, and the date of publication. Some of these have Sylvia Plath's annotations and underlining.
      - List beginning "I have published the following poems in magazines", 1959; 3 pages 3 pages (2 leaves) (Box 14.2, Folder 308, Item 1)
        Original and carbon typescript of published poems. These pages may be drafts for Sylvia Plath's Yaddo application in 1959. In addition to the list of her publications, she writes about a "project," beginning: "The general nature of my project is to complete my book of poems, The Bull Of Bendylaw, …"
      - List beginning "Published Articles & Stories", probably 1959-1961; 2 pages (Box 14.2, Folder 308, Item 2)
        Typescript list with entries dated from 1956-1959. Sylvia Plath's handwritten additions include publications in 1960 and 1961.
      - "List of Publications", 1961 August (Box 14.2, Folder 308, Item 3)
        Carbon typescript with entries dated from 1957 through August 1961.
      - Typescript and holograph lists of poems by Sylvia Plath annotated where published, undated; 1 pages (1 typescript page); 4 pages 4 pages (3 leaves) (Box 14.2, Folder 308, Item 4)
        One page typescript and 4 pages holograph lists of Sylvia Plath's poems, annotated with where published, and with Sylvia Plath's underlining and additional annotations. The back of one half-page is a typescript, with annotation by Sylvia Plath, of the end of her poem "Leaving Early." The back of another half-page is the beginning of a typed letter (1961 September 16) to Jennifer Hassell (A.M. Health & Co., London) concerning the possible publication of her own and Ted Hughes' books for children.
  - Reviews, approximately 1957-1962; 6; .25 linear feet (7 folders)
    Arranged in alphabetical order by the title of the item reviewed.
    This subseries contains typescripts, galleys, and printed versions of Sylvia Plath's reviews of other's works.
    - Typescript review of The Emperor's Oblong Pancake, The Three Robbers, and The Funny Thing, 1962 May 18; 3 pages (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Carbon typescript of Sylvia Plath's review of three children's books: Peter Hughes The Emperor's Oblong Pancake; Tomi Ungerer, The Three Robbers; Wanda Gag, The Funny Thing.The review also includes seven other books "also recommended." One manuscript revision on page 3 and in Plath's hand at top: New Statesman, May 18, 1962. Typed name and address (Devon).
    - Typeset galley proof of "General Jodpur's Conversion" (Box 15, Folder 2)
      Typeset galley proof of "General Jodpur's Conversion," a review of Janet Charters, The General; Jacqueline Ayer, A Wish for Little Sister; Gaby Baldner, Joba and the Wild Boar; and brief mentions of five other books. Two handwritten corrections by Plath. Published in The New Statesman.
    - Typescript review of Lord Byron's Wife, 3 pages (Box 15, Folder 3)
      Typescript (carbon), review of Lord Byron's Wife by Malcolm Ewin. Handwritten. revision and corrections by Sylvia Plath. Typed name and address (Devon).
    - Typescript review of Opal Whiteley, The Unsolved Mystery. Together with Opal Whiteley's Diary, approximately 1962; 2 pages (Box 15, Folder 3.1)
      Carbon typescript of Sylvia Plath's review of Opal Whiteley by E.S. Bradburne (London: Putnam, 1962?). Typescript has some handwritten revision by Plath.
    - Galley proof of "Oregonian Originals", 1962 November 9; 2 pages (Box 15, Folder 3.2)
      Galley proof of "Oregonian Originals", a review of Opal Whiteley, The Wonderful Button, Little Blue and Little Yellow, and Punch and Judy Carry On, as well as five other books "also recommended." "New Statesman - 40" is at the type of the column and "NSproof for correction; please ring Wed. morning if any changes" is typed at the top. Review published in New Statesman, page 660, 1962 November 9.
    - Photocopy of printed version of review of The Stones of Troy, summer 1957 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      Photocopy of printed version of Sylvia Plath's review of The Stones of Troy by C.A. Trypanis. Printed version from Gemini, pages 98-103, summer 1957.
      Gift of Peter K. Steinberg, 5/2013.
    - Typescript review of The Wonderful Button, Little Blue and Little Yellow, and Punch and Judy Carry On, 3 pages (Box 15, Folder 4.1, Item 1)
      Carbon typescript of Sylvia Plath's review of three children's books: The Wonderful Button, by Evan Hunter; Little Blue and Little Yellow, by Leo Lionni; and Punch and Judy Carry On, by Elizabeth and Gerald Rose. Review also includes five other books "also recommended." Typescript has one handwritten correction by Plath on page one, and typed name and Devon address.
    - Photocopy of original typescript review of The Wonderful Button (Box 15, Folder 4.1, Item 2)
      Photocopy of the typescript originals of Syliva Plath's review of The Wonderful Button. Typescript contains numerous handwritten corrections and annotations by Plath and was typed of the backs of holograph and typed drafts of her poem "Getting There."
      Original filed with: Writings. Poems. Getting There.-0
  - Short stories, approximately 1949-1977; circa 1950-1978; 7; 1.25 linear feet (1 box; 4 folders in 2 oversize boxes)
    This subseries is comprised of published and upublshied works of short fiction by Sylvia Plath.
    - Holograph of "About a year ago I was babysitting...", undated; 4 pages 4 pages (last blank) (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Holograph of the short story "About a year ago I was babysitting..." Includes a pen and ink illustration of a child's head. Written on paper with printed letterhead: Connecticut General Life Insurance Company, From: E.H. Carroll, General Agent, Schenectady, N.Y.
    - Photocopy of typescript of unidentified story "Alison" (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Typescript (photocopy only), pages 10 and 11. Several handwritten. corrections by Plath. Typed on verso of drafts of Plath's poem "Sheep in Fog." The folder also contains a fragment of another unidentified story with a character named Alison (From Ted Hughes Papers, Emory University, Atlanta, GA).
      Originals filed with: Writings. Poems. Sheep in Fog.
    - Printed version of "All the Dead Dears", summer 1957 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      Printed version of "All the Dead Dears" in Gemini, volume 1, number 2, page 53, summer 1957. Annotated by Aurelia Plath. Also includes three poems by Ted Hughes: "Famous Poet," "Wind," and "Macaw and Little Miss." Also includes Plath's book review of The stones of Troy. Lane & Stevens 279.
    - Typescript of "Among the Bumblebees", 9 pages (Box 15, Folder 8, Item 1)
      Original and carbon typescript of "Among the Bumblebees," the last page a duplicate of page 4, crossed out. The typescript has a few handwritten annotations by Aurelia Plath in addition to her note attached to the title page that reads, "This is the original, which, in places, differs from the piece published in 'Johnny Panic.'" Typescript has typed namd and address (Smith College Lawrence House).
    - Printed version of "And Summer Will Not Come Again", 1950 August (Box 43, Folder 6)
      Two copies of the printed version in Seventeen August 1950, pages 191 and 275-6. First copy, Lane & Stevens 282. Second copy has "From the Library of Sylvia Plath" annotated by her on the front cover. Additionally annotated by Aurelia Plath including "The first published story (preceded by 45 rejections!)".
      Annotated copy gift of Aurelia S. Plath, 12/03/1983.
    - Printed version of "The Daughters of Blossom Street", 1960 May (Box 15, Folder 9)
      Printed version from The London Magazine volume 7, pages 34-48. "London Magazine: May 1960" is written at the top in Sylvia Plath's hand. Annotated by Sylvia PLath. Lane & Stevens 290.
    - Printed version of "The Day Mr. Prescott Died", 1956 October 20 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      Printed version in Granta volume LX, number 1166, pages 20-23, with Aurelia Plath's typed label on the front cover.
    - Typescript of "Day of Success", 17 pages (Box 15, Folder 11, Item 1)
      Typescript of "Day of Success" with typed name and address (London, Chalcot Square). Pages are punched with two holes on the left-hand side.
    - Printed version of "Den of Lions", 1951 May (Box 43.1, Folder 8)
      Printed version from Seventeen 1951 May, pages 126-7 and 144-5. "Third prize, short-story contest." Includes color illustration by Floyd Johnson.
    - Printed version of "Den of Lions", 1951 May (Box 43.1, Folder 8)
      Printed version from Seventeen 1951 May, pages 126-7 and 144-5. "From the library of Sylvia Plath" annotated on the cover by her and Aurelia Plath.
    - Holograph of "An Evening at the Hoftizers", undated; 2 pages (Box 15, Folder 12)
      Holograph of "An Evening at the Hoftizers", not in Lane & Stevens.
    - Printed version of "The Fifteen-Dollar Eagle", autumn 1960 (Box 15, Folder 13, Item 1)
      Printed version from The Sewanee Review volume 68, pages 603-618. "SEWANEE REVIEW: AUTUMN 1960" is typed at the head of the page. "Return to: Olwyn Hughes" is handwritten. Lane and Stevens 295.
    - Printed version of "The Fifteen-Dollar Eagle", autumn 1960 (Box 15, Folder 13, Item 2)
      Printed version from The Sewanee Review volume 68, pages 603-618. "Sewanee Review: Autumn 1960" is at hte top of the first page in Sylvia Plath's hand. Land and Stevens 295
    - Typescript of "The Fifty-Ninth Bear", 17 pages (Box 15, Folder 14, Item 1)
      Typescript carbons of "The Fifty-Ninth Bear" with extensive handwritten revisions by Plath. "London Mag" is at the head of the first page in Plath's hand. Includes typed name and Wellesley address.
    - Typescript of "The Fifty-Ninth Bear", 15 pages (Box 15, Folder 14, Item 15)
      Typescript with a few corrections of typing errors and one handwritten revision by Plath on page 13. Includes typed name and London, Chalcot Square address.
    - Holograph of "The Garden Party", undated; 4 pages 4 pages (1 blank); Paper has 3 holes punched on the left side. (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Printed version of "In the Mountains", fall 1954 (Box 15, Folder 15.1)
      Printed version in Smith Review fall 1954, pages 2-5. "Merry Christmas to mother from Sylvia 1954" is inscribed on the front cover. Annotated by Aurelia Plath. The issue also includes Sylvia Plath's poem "Circus in Three Rings."
    - Holograph of "Initiation", undated; 1 pages (Box 15, Folder 16)
      Early draft holograph with manuscript title "Heather-Birds eyebrows" and illustrated with pen and ink drawings of women.
    - Printed version of "Initiation", 1953 January (Box 43.1, Folder 10)
      Printed version in Seventeen 1953 January, pages 64 and 92-94, with accompanying woodcut illustration by Marjory Carolyn Clark on page 64. "From the library of Sylvia Plath" is annotated on the front cover by her and by Aurelia Plath.
    - Photocopy of a typescript of page 15 of "The Invisible Man", undated (Box 15, Folder 17)
      Photocopy of page 15 of "The Invisible Man" on the back kof a revised holograph and typescript of Plath's poem "Berck-Plage."
      Original filed in Writings. Poems. Berck-Plage: Box 7, Folder 30, item 3.
    - Holograph of plot summary for "Irene", undated; 2 pages (Box 15, Folder 18)
      Plot summary for a short story about an Irish maid, written on an index card.
    - Typescript of "Johnny Panic and the Bible of Dreams", 23 pages (Box 15, Folder 19, Item 1)
      Carbon typescript with typed name and Wellesley address.
    - Typescript of "Johnny Panic and the Bible of Dreams", 23 pages (Box 15, Folder 19, Item 2)
      Typescript with handwritten revisions on pages 3 and 10, with typed name and address (London, Chalcot Square changed in Plath's hand to London, Fitzroy Road).
    - Printing specimen for "Johnny Panic and the Bible of Dreams" (book), 1977; 4 pages (Box 15, Folder 19.1)
      Printing specimen for the Faber & Faber edition 1977. Three pages of text and last page lists printing and imposition specifications and instructions, with blank space for approvals. "Specimen submitted 25 March 1977". Some areas of dirt and inky fingerprints.
    - Typescript of "The Lucky Stone", 16 pages (Box 15, Folder 20, Item 1)
      Carbon typescript with correction and typing errors. "Sold 15.15.0 by Jennifer Hassell" written in Plath's hand at the top. Includes typed name and address (London, Chalcot Square).
    - Color photocopy of printed version of "The Lucky Stone", 1961 October 28 (Box 15, Folder 20, Item 2)
      Color photocopies of printed version with title "The Perfect Place" in My Weekly number 2498, pages 3-7 and 31.
      Gift of Peter K. Steinberg, 3/27/2009.
    - Typescript of "Mothers", 11 pages (Box 15, Folder 21, Item 1)
      Carbon typescript with a few handwritten revisions and corrections, typed name and Devon address.
    - Typescript of "Mothers", 11 pages (Box 15, Folder 21, Item 2)
      Typescript originals with a few handwritten revisions and corrections in Plath's hand. Corrections are reflected in the printed version, with the title "The Mothers' Union." Includes typed name and Devon address.
    - "Printed version of "Mothers", 1972 October (Box 15, Folder 21, Item 3)
      Printed version in McCall's volume C, number 1, pages 80, 126, 128, 130, and 142. Annotated by Aurelia Plath, including a typed label on the front cover: "p. 80 'The Mothers' Union' story by Sylvia, originally intended as a segment of what would have been Book III had she not burned the Ms. for Book II." Aurelia Plath also has heavily annotated (partly in shorthand) the article "My Parents Are My Friends" by Joyce Maynard.
    - Holograph of "The music wailed out from the radio...", undated; 3 pages (first 3 pages of a 12-page stapled section of lined notebook paper) (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Typescript and holograph draft of "The New Zealand spinach was good that morning...", probably 1950; 10 pages (last blank) (Box 15, Folder 23)
      Typescript and holograph draft illustrated with three pen and ink figure sketches.
    - Typeset galley proof of "Ocean 1212-W", 1963 August 29; 3 pages (Box 15, Folder 24, Item 1)
      Typeset galley proof published in The Listener volume 70, pages 312-313. One handwritten correction on page 1. The proof is headed "The writer and his background." Typed note from the editor requests return of corrected proof by Friday, August 23.